<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The grievances given in by the ministers before the Parliament holden in June 1633 Propositions concerning kneeling before the bread in the sacrament. Master William Coupers letter to the Bishop of Dumblane. The Bishops instruction to Master Gawin Hammiltoun, Bishop of Galloway. Mr. George Gladstones letter to the King. Master William Struthers letter to the Earle of Airth.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1635</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 52 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11741</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22034</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106162</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841885</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841885</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6500</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11741)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6500)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1334:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The grievances given in by the ministers before the Parliament holden in June 1633 Propositions concerning kneeling before the bread in the sacrament. Master William Coupers letter to the Bishop of Dumblane. The Bishops instruction to Master Gawin Hammiltoun, Bishop of Galloway. Mr. George Gladstones letter to the King. Master William Struthers letter to the Earle of Airth.</title>
                  <author>Spottiswood, John, 1565-1639. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>31, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>S.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Printed abroad :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed Anno 1635.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to John Spottiswood by STC.</note>
                  <note>"Printed abroad" from STC.</note>
                  <note>Formerly also STC 10405.</note>
                  <note>Usually bound with STC 739.5: Certaine arguments and motives, of speciall moment, to abolish government of our church by bishops.</note>
                  <note>Some print show-through, and some pages marked.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bishops --  Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6500:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6500:1"/>
            <p>The grievances given in by the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters before the Parliament hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in June 1633.
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Propoſitions concerning kneeling before the bread in the Sacrament.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Maſter WILLIAM COUPERS Letter to the Bishop of <hi>Dumblane.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The Bishops inſtruction to Maſter</hi> Gawin Hammiltoun, <hi>Bishop of</hi> Galloway.</item>
                  <item>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>George Gladſtones</hi> letter to the King.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Maſter</hi> William Struthers <hi>letter to the Earle of</hi> Airth.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Printed Anno 1635.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:6500:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:6500:2"/>
            <head>The grievances given in by the Miniſters before the laſt Parliament in Iune 1633.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Miniſters ſtanding for the preſervation of the puritie of religion in Doctrine worship, and governement, aſſayed ſundrie meanes to have his MAIESTIE rightlie informed of the eſtate of our Kirk, but the ſucceſſe was not anſwerable to their expectation. Yet having the opportunitie of his Majeſt. coming to his native countrie of</hi> Scotland <hi>to be crowned, and hold his firſt Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, they adviſed upon ſome grievances to be preſented to his Maieſtie and Eſtates. It was ordained by act of Parliament</hi> 1594. <hi>that foure of everie eſtate should conveene twentie dayes before the beginning of the Parliament, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider all articles and petitions, which were to be given in, that ſuch things onlie might be put in forme, and preſented to the Lords of the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles in time of Parliament, as were reaſonable and neceſſarie, and that ſuch, as were imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent and frivolous, might be rejected. But it was not determined who should make choice of the perſons. Yet this was not obſerved before the laſt Parliament. But upon the 16 of May</hi> 1633. <hi>intimation was made by Proclamation, that all</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:6500:3"/> 
               <hi>ſuch, as purpoſed to give in any articles or pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions, deliver the ſame to the Clerk Regiſter betwixt and the firſt day of Iune, to be preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by him to ſuch of the eſtates and counſell, as should be appointed to hear and conſider them. The miniſters fearing not to be heard otherwiſe, appointed one of their diſtreſſed bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren</hi> Master Thomas Hogge <hi>to preſent their grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances to him, which he preſented and delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and tooke inſtruments thereupon in the hands of a Notair.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Grievances &amp; petitions concerning the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordered eſtate of the reformed Kirk with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in this Realme of Scotland, preſented upon the 29 day of May 1633. by me <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Thomas Hogge</hi> Miniſter of the Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell, in mine owne name, and in name of others of the miniſtrie, likewiſe grieved, to Sir <hi>John Hay</hi> Clerk of Regiſter, to be preſented by him to ſuch as ought accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the order appointed, conſider them, that thereafter they may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to his Maieſtie and Eſtates, which are to be aſſembled at the next inſuing Parliament.</head>
               <p>THE opportunitie of this ſolemne meeting of your gratious Majeſtie and the honourable Eſtates con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veened
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:6500:3"/> in this high court of Parliament, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of our dutie to God and the reformed Kirk with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in this Realme of Scotland, where we ſerve by our mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrie, constraines us to preſent in all humilitie to your Highnes and Eſtates preſentlie aſſembled thoſe our juſt grievances and reaſonable petitions following:</p>
               <p n="1">1 Albeit vote in Parliament was not abſolutlie granted to miniſters provided to prelacies, but onlie up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch conditions as his Highnes of happie memorie, and the generall aſſemblies of the Kirk should agree up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which is evident by the remit and proviſion ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in the act of Parliament holden at Edinburgh in December 1597. And albeit the manner of their ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and admiſsion to the office of Commiſsionarie, and the particular conditions and cautions to be obſerved by Miniſters vote in Parliament in name of the Kirk af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter long diſputation, were agreed upon by his Maieſtie preſent in perſon, and the generall aſſemblie and were appoint<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d by them to be inſert in the bodie of the act of Parliament, which was to be made concerning that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, Some Miniſters notwithſtanding have beene and are admitted to vote in parliament in name of the Kirk as abſolutlie, as if the act of Parliament did containe no ſuch reference, and as if his Majeſtie with the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall aſſemblie had not agreed upon the manner of their election and admiſsion to that office, or upon any limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations; wherby the Kirk hath ſustained great hurt &amp; prejudice in her liberties and priviledges, and ſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie by their frequent tranſgreſsing the first of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions although grounded upon the verie law of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and nations. That nothing be proponed by them in parliament, counſell or convention in name of the Kirck without expreſs warrant &amp; direction from the Kirck, under the paine of depoſition from their office; Neither ſhall they keep ſilence, nor conſent in any of the ſaid conventions to any thing that may be preiudiciall to the libertie &amp; weal of the Kirck,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:6500:4"/> under the ſaid paine. And the ſecond. That they ſhall be bound at every generall aſſemblie to give account<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ment the diſcharging of their commiſsion ſince the aſſemblie preceeding, and ſhall ſubmit themſelfes to their cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and ſtand to their determination whatſoever without appellation, and shall ſeek and obtaine ratification of their doings at the ſaid aſſemblie under the paine of infamie and excommunication. Therefore our humble ſupplication is, that the execution of the acts of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of matters belonging to the Kirk, to which they have voted in name of the Kirk, without any authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie or allowance from the generall aſſemblies of the Kirk, be ſuſpended, till the Kirk be heard, and that in time coming miniſters have no otherwiſe vote in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, but according to the proviſion of the act of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and the order of their entrie to the office of that commiſsionarie and limitation foreſaid agreed upon, as ſaid is.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Seing ratifications of acts and conſtitutions of the Kirk can not be conſtrued to be a benefite or favour to the Kirk, unleſſe the ratifications paſſe according to the meaning of the Kirk, and the tenor of the ſaid acts and conſtitutions without omiſsion, addition, or altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of clauſes, articles, or words of importance, and that in the ratification of the act of the aſſemblie holden at Glaſgow anno 1610. which paſt in Parliament holden 1612. under the name of explanation, ſundrie clauſes and articles were omitted, as the ſubjection of Bishops in all things concerning their life, converſation, office and benefice, to the cenſure of the generall aſſemblie, the cenſure of Bishops incaſe the ſtay the cenſure of excommunication, the continuing of the exerciſe of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine weeklie, the neceſsitie of the teſtificat and aſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the miniſtrie of the bounds for the admiſsion of miniſters, and other clauſes and articles are added and inſert, as the different degrees of Archbishops and Bishops, the power of giving collation of benefices gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:6500:4"/> to Bishops, the diſponing of benefices falling in their hands <hi>jure devoluto,</hi> the appointing of Moderators in dioceſan Synods incaſe of their abſence, and ſome words of the oath are changed: By all which omiſsions, additions, and alterations, the Kirk hath ſuſtained, and doth ſuſtaine great hurt in her Iuriſdiction and diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline. Our humble deſire therfore is, that the Kirk may be liberat from the prejudice of thoſe omiſsions, addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and alterations of the act foreſaid.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Notwithſtanding the generall aſſemblies have beene holden from the time of reformation till the year 1603. at least once in the year and oftner <hi>pro re nata,</hi> provinciall Synods twice in the year, weeklie meetings for exerciſes and presbyteries everie weeke, for matters to be treated in them reſpective, &amp; their liberties were ratified in parliament anno 1592. and by that as a most powerfull meane, bleſſed be God, peace and puritie of religion were maintained: And in the aſſemblie holden at Glaſgow 1610. when Commiſsioners voters in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament provided to prelacies were made lyable to the cenſures of the generall aſſemblie, It was acknowledged that the neceſsitie of the Kirk craved, that there should be yearlie generall aſſemblies, And the Miniſtrie were then aſſured, that libertie would be granted upon their requeſt, whereby they were induced to condeſcend ſo farre to the act then made as they did, which act alſo beareth in the verie entrie thereof a request to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie, that generall aſſemblies may be holden in all times coming once in the year, or preciſlie at a ſet and certaine time, Nevertheles the wonted libertie of hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding generall aſſemblies is ſuppreſſed, the order of the provinciall Synods confounded, presbyteries in a great part diſordered and neglected, whereby diviſions have entered into the Kirk, Miniſters are become negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:6500:5"/> in their callings, and ſcandalous in their lifes, the godlie are heavilie grieved, the weake are ſcandalized, erroneous doctrine is delivered in Kirks and Schooles without controlement, the Commiſsioners voters in parliament lye untried and uncenſured, and atheiſme and poperie increaſe: Our humble deſire is therefore, that the acts of parliament made in favours of the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies of the Kirk, and ſpeciallie the act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment holden at Edinburgh in Iune 1592. be reviſed and ratified in this preſent parliament.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Notwithſtanding the obſervation of feſtivall dayes, privat baptiſme, privat communion, epiſcopall confirmation of children, have beene rejected by this our reformed Kirk, ſince the beginning of the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, and it hath beene declared by act of parliament in the year 1567. that ſuch onlie were to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged members of this reformed Kirk, as did participat of the Sacraments as they were then right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie miniſtred, which was without kneeling in the act of receaving the ſacramentall elements of the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, or immediate diſpenſing of the ſame to everie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municant by the miniſter; And that it was ſtatute and ordained in the ſame parliament that all Kings should give their oath at their coronation to meantaine the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion then profeſſed, and that forme of miniſtration of the ſacraments which then was uſed: Nevertheles pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors and people adhering to their former profeſsion and practiſe are nicknamed <hi>Puritans</hi> and threatned, not onlie without any good warrant, but beſide the tenor of the act of perth aſſemblie, which containeth no ſtrict injunction, and contrary to the meaning of the voters, and to the proceedings of that aſſemblie, where it was profeſſed that none should be preſſed with obedience to that act: Therfore we humblie intreat that by ratifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:6500:5"/> of the acts of parliament made before that aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie and by ſuch wayes as shall ſeeme good to your gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Majeſtie, &amp; honourable Eſtates aſſembled, your Majeſties good people, Paſtors &amp; Profeſſors may both be purged from ſuch foule aſperſions, and may be freed from all dangers and fears which may occurre by occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of that act of perth.</p>
               <p n="5">5 Albeit it be determined by the generall aſſemblies of this our reformed Kirk, what oathes Miniſters should take at the time of their admiſsion or ordination, yet there is a new forme of oath deviſed and urged by the admitters or ordainers, upon intrants to the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrie, together with ſubſcription to certaine articles de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed by them without direction and warrant from any aſſemblie of the Kirk, yea or act of parliament, whereby the entrie to the miniſtrie is shut upon the best quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and others leſse able are obtruded upon the people to their great griefe and hazard of their ſoules: Our humble petition therefore is, that all ſuch oathes and ſubſcriptio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s urged upon miniſters at their entrie or tranſplantation, may be diſcharged.</p>
               <p n="6">6 Notwithſtanding there be conſtitutions of the kirk and lawes of the countrie for cenſuring of miniſters before the ordinarie judicatours eccleſiaſticall, yet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to that order, miniſters are ſuſpended, ſilenced and deprived, and that for matters meerly eccleſiaſticall before other judicatours, which are not eſtabliſhed by the authority or order of the countrey and kirk: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our humble petition is, that miniſters deſerving cenſure be no otherwiſe cenſured, then the order of the kirk doth preſcrive, and that ſuch as are otherwiſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placed be ſuffered to ſerve in the miniſtrie, as before.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Preſenter attended in</hi> Edinburg <hi>to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pear, if need were before ſuch, as were to conveene</hi>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:6500:6"/> 
                  <hi>to conſider the articles and petitions, which were given in to the Clerk Regiſter. But there was no appearance of any ſuch convention. The Miniſters therefore directed the brother above named to preſent the ſupplication following to his Majeſtie, which he did upon the fifteen day of Iunie in the Caſtle of</hi> Dalkeith, <hi>the ſame day that he was to make his entrie in</hi> Edinburgh.</p>
               <p>This happie occaſion with ſtrong deſires long waited for by your Majeſties most humble and loving ſubjects the Paſtors and Profeſſors of the reformed religion within this your Majeſties Kingdome of Scotland. The great fame, which hath often filled our eares, of your Majeſties most pious and princelie inclination to reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and righteouſnes, whence this Kirk and Kingdome from their ſingular intereſſe in your Majeſties birth &amp; baptiſme, have reaſon to looke at this time for a confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table influence: the bodie of this Kingdome in heart joyning with us, and onelie waiting for the least word from your Majeſties mouth: The conſcience which we have and which we trust is manifest to all men that we are ſeeking neither riches nor honours to our ſelfes, but that the ſumme and ſubſtance of our deſires is to procure the advancement of the Kingdome of Ieſus Christ, and to ſee your Majeſties flourishing eſtate, in your King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes: All theſe and each of them move us to intreat in all humilitie your gratious Maieſtie to be favourable to our petitions, which we have delivered to the Clerk of Regiſter to be preſented to your Majeſtie and Eſtates at the approaching Parliament, that they may be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered and receave a gratious anſwer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The King read the petition at length. Yet there was no more heard of our grievances either among the Lords of the articles, or in open Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:6500:6"/> 
                  <hi>where nothing cometh in voting, but that which firſt muſt paſſe the Lords of the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, and uſuallie what paſſeth through their hands is concluded by the whole Eſtates in pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blike. Not onlie were our grievances ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, but alſo all former acts concerning the Kirk, were ratified. Howbeit it was wel knowne that ſundrie former acts had wrought great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbance in our Kirk. An act alſo in particular concerning the common habits of Kirkmen, (not of ſurplice or other like ſuperſtitious ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures, as many miſtake) was ratified and made a point of the royall prerogative. Small hope had we of any better event conſidering the depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance either of Noblemen upon the Kings fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour for the recoverie of their brocken eſtates, or of ſome other men for preferment, or the fear of others to loſe it, all knowing verie well the Kings bent and inclination.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the better clearing of the equitie of our grievances, I will ſet downe theſe few obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Great oppoſition was made by manie worthie men of the miniſtrie to Miniſters vote in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, convention, or counſell, and not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reaſon. When it was carried by pluralitie of procured voces in a generall aſſemblie holden at</hi> Dundie <hi>anno</hi> 1597. <hi>againſt which and the two former aſſemblies M.</hi> Iohn Davidſon <hi>proteſted, the nixt care of the ſincerer ſort was to have the Commiſſioner voter in Parliament tyed to a certaine forme of admiſſion, and to ſome cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that he degener not into a Roman or An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glican Bishop.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:6500:7"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>He was to be recommended to his Majeſtie, by the generall aſſemblie, and to be admitted by the Synod as it then ſtood in integritie. The firſt two cautions ye have heard in the grievan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. By the third, the commiſſioner voter in Parliament was bound not to prejudge the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion of other Kirks planted or to be planted. By the fourth he was bound not to delapidar or diſpone any part of his benefice without the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and conſent of his Majeſtie and the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall aſſemblie, and to interdite himſelfe to that effect. By the fifth,</hi> He was bound to attend faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully upon his own particular congregation, where he ſhall be miniſter, in all the points of a paſtor, and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anent to be ſubject to the triall and cenſure of his own presbyterie and provinciall aſſembly, as any other mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter that beareth not commiſsion. <hi>By the ſixt cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> In the adminiſtration of diſcipline, collation of benefices, viſitation, and all other points of eccleſiaſticall government, he ſhall neither uſurpe nor acclaime to himſelfe any power or juriſdiction, farther then any of the reſt of his brethren, under the paine of deprivation. <hi>By the ſeventh,</hi> That in presbyteries, provinciall and generall aſſemblies, he ſhal behave himſelf in all things, and be ſubject to their cenſure, as any of the brethren of the preſbyterie. <hi>By the eight,</hi> At his admiſsion to the office of commiſsionarie, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe and all other points ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie he ſhall ſwear and ſubſcrive to fulfill under the penalties foreſaid, otherwiſe not to be admitted. <hi>By the ninth,</hi> In caſe he be depoſed by the generall aſſembly, ſynod, or presbyterie from his office of the miniſtrie, he ſhall loſe his vote in Parliament <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> and his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefice ſhall vaike.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Such as plotted the courſe of Epiſcopacie and</hi>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:6500:7"/> 
                  <hi>aſpired to prelacies were conſtrained for the preſent to condeſcend to theſe cautions, but were not minded to ſtand to one jot of them longer then they ſaw occaſions to breake looſe. Becauſe they were made countable by theſe cautions to the generall aſſemblies, they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured firſt a prorogation of the diets of the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies by the Kings authoritie, and at laſt the bereaving of the Kirk of all libertie to indict any aſſemblies, that ſo they might bee freed from making any count at all. After they had gathered ſtrength and power to overrule aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies of their owne deviſing, and after that ſome of the Miniſtrie were banished, others confined, a third ſort drawen up to court, they procured a convention at</hi> Linlithgow <hi>anno</hi> 1606. <hi>of Noblemen and Miniſters nominat by them and recommended by the King to the presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries to be ſent to that meeting. The name of a generall aſſemblie was concealed in the Kings miſſives. But ſoone after presbyteries were charged with letters of horning to accept the conſtant moderators choſen by that meeting, ſuch as were ſtyled vulgarly Bishops in reſpect of their benefices to be moderators of the preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteries where they made reſidence. Synods likewiſe were urged to accept theſe Bishops for conſtant moderators, howbeit no ſuch thing was concluded at that meeting but their acte falſified.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This moderation did not ſatisfie their ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious humour, nor was it well accepted by preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteries or the Synodes. In the yeare</hi> 1610. <hi>they were armed with the power of the high</hi>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:6500:8"/> 
                  <hi>commiſſion, of which they were not cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and without conſent of the Eſtates, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trairy to an act of Parliament Anno</hi> 1584. <hi>to ſilence &amp; deprive, fine and incarcerat Miniſters, to command them to excommunicat ſuch as in their judgement deſerved that cenſure, and to fine and impriſon other whatſoever ſubjects. After that they become thus great and terrible, and now able to extort any thing from ſervile miniſters, they procured an aſſemblie to be hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den at</hi> Glaſgow <hi>ſoone after like that other at</hi> Linlithgow, <hi>but that there was more gold delt among mercenarie miniſters at this aſſemblie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Soone after three of their number went to court to be conſecrat Bishops, returned &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated the reſt of their fellowes, no ſuch thing being concluded at that meeting as the office of a Dioceſan Bishop, Anglican or Roman, that is, to be the proper Paſtor of all the congregations within the Diocie, the power of ordination reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in him, and of juriſdiction flowing from him. The presbyteries and Synods were onlie tyed to theſe who were called Bishops in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of their benefices in the points, and in the manner expreſſed &amp; upon truſt that they should be lyable to the cenſure of ordinarie and ſet ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall aſſemblies. But they were not content with ſundrie articles of that act, howbeit the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblie was overruled by themſelfes, and they conſented, to the end that the Miniſters there conveened might be induted to yeeld ſo farre as they did. Therefore when the act was rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied anno</hi> 1612. <hi>they conſented in Parliament to additions, alterations, and omiſſions, of ſundrie</hi>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:6500:8"/> 
                  <hi>clauſes, as no doubt they had deviſed themſelfes before. In the yeare</hi> 1617. <hi>they conſented in Parliament to the election of Bishops by Deans and Chapters, which was inhibited by the acts of the aſſemblie holden</hi> 1578. <hi>and condemned in the ſecond booke of policie as popish. It was likewiſe farre different from the forme of ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and admiſſion agreed upon with their owne conſents in the generall aſſemblies. What was proponed in Parliament for their advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was granted by the Eſtates, and conſented to be themſelfes as no doubt they had deviſed. So they were their owne carvers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In end they brought in popish ceremonies to vex the Miniſters and Profeſſors, and to give them ſome other ſubject to worke upon, then to medle with themſelfes, and their uſurped authoritie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Becauſe they are conſcious to themſelfes of the nullitie of their aſſemblies, and fear to want the concurrence of Synods and presbyteries they draw Miniſters &amp; Profeſſors before their court of high commiſſion. But if this court were not fortified and aſſiſted by the Lords of ſecret counſell by whom it was firſt authoriſed, their power in the high commiſſion would be litle re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded. Our bondage then reſolves upon the counſell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whatſoever be, the uſurpation of the Prelats, the Miniſtrie and Profeſſors are not to be excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. Firſt for acknowledging or not opponing to their aſſemblies. For the ſafetie of religion dependeth not upon aſſemblies of whatſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever kinde, but upon the libertie of free and</hi>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:6500:9"/> 
                  <hi>right conſtitute aſſemblies. As in the common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weale he were not to be thought a faithfull pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triot, who would not ſtand as much for the libertie of a Parliament as his owne poſſeſſions, becauſe the ſafetie of all other liberties ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in the preſervation of maine liberty. Nixt, becauſe they continue in ſubjection, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding we have not the libertie of ordinarie and ſet aſſemblies to cenſure them according to the cautions and acts agreed unto by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfes. Thirdlie, becauſe they give farther obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, then is required by the acts of their owne aſſemblies, as if they had an abſolute power to direct and enjoyne as pleaſeth them. But the firſt is the fountaine of all our miſchief.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I have here ſubjoyned certaine propoſitions concerning adoration before the bread in the Sacrament without the knowledge of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, who is knowne to be learned and judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Beſides that manifest and groſſe kinde of idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, whereby divine or religious worſhip is given unto the creature in ſtead of God, there is another more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret and ſubtile ſort, which rendereth not divine wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip unto the creature as it is conſidered in it ſelf, but as it carrieth a certaine relation and reſpect unto God, who is to be worſhipped for himſelfe, and therefore is commonly called <hi>Relative worship.</hi> The reformed Kirks convince the Papiſts of manifold. Idolatrie of this kinde, and howſoever the Papiſts gather toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther many fig-tree leafes to hide their nakedneſse, yet there is nothing more certain, then that both the Gentiles and Iewes pleaſed themſelfes in this ſort of worſhip, as may appeare from Roman. 1. 20. and 23.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:6500:9"/> Deut. 4. 12. and 15. and many other places.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As in the groſſer kinde of idolatrie it matters not, as touching the point of idolatrie it ſelf, whither the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of adoration, and that which we worſhip with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine honour, be the invention of our owne head, or the creature of God, as the Sunne, Moone, or Starres, or made by our hands as an Image, or ſome thing ordained of God, And finallie whither it be a thing conſecrated or not for the adoration of the bread in the Sacrament is idolatrie, no leſſe then the adoration of the Sunne in the firmament, or the adoration of an image the worke of mans hands. For their error is more tollerable who worship for God a ſtatue of gold or ſilver, or an image of any other matter, as the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles worſhipped their Gods, or a red cloath lifted up upon a ſpeare, which is reported of the Lappians, or living creatures as ſome time the Aegyptians nor theirs who worship a piece bread. Coſter. Enchir. C. 12. In like manner, in the other ſort of worship which is rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, it is all one matter touching the point of idolatrie, whither the ſecondarie or ſubordinat object of our ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and that which participats of the worship of God, be a thing naturall, as the Sunne or the Moone, or a thing artificiall, as an image, or ſome thing ordained of God, but for an other end, as the Braſen Serpent, or a thing conſecrated of God, but not to be worshipped, as the Sacramentall bread, for although there be a very wide difference amongst thoſe things in reſpect of will-worſhip, And becauſe nothing can be a mean of the worſhip of God, but that which is ordained of God, and the Sacrament is a meane of Gods worſhip, an image is not a meane, yet in the point of idolatrie there can be no difference at all, becauſe no creature of what ſomever kinde can ſo much as take of the worship of God with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the guiltines of idolatrie.</p>
               <p n="3">3. We fall into two evils, when we adore before an image, one is, when we make the image a meane or midle
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:6500:10"/> of the worship of God without a warrant from God, whence it is that adoration before an image is will-worſhip, and although it had no other evill in it but this one, it behoveth to be (by interpretation as they uſe to ſpeake or by conſequent) idolatrie, for whoſoever ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointeth of his owne head a new manner or meane of divine worſhip, by conſequence alſo appointeth an other God, which he thinks delyteth in that forme of worſhip. The other evill is that adoration before an image is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly and formable idolatrie, becauſe thereby religious worſhip is rendered unto another then unto God, and in ſome meaſure and degree the image is made partaker of the worſhip of God, which is cleared at large by the divines of the reformed Kirks. Now in our adoration before the bread we are free of the former of the two evils, becauſe the Sacrament is a meane of worſhip au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorized by God, but we cannot poſsibly be free of the other evill, becauſe the adoration before the bread, and before an image are altogether a like in reſpect of the participation of divine worſhip. They who are enemies to images (ſaith Vaſquez in his 2 booke of adorat. diſp. 8. c. 13.) and uſe images onlie for hiſtorie and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, doe not bow their knees nor proſtrat themſelves before them: for ſo they ſhould adore them, with an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall ſigne of worſhip. He who is religiouſlie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrat before the croſſe (ſayeth the Biſhop op Spalato booke 7. page 293) he must have the croſſe for the object of adoration. Although images were meanes of worſhip ordained of God, ſuch as the Sacrament is, yet were it not lawfull to adore before them. And the arguments whereby our divines prove the worſhip of images to be idolatrie, aime not at this point to ſhew that images are not lawfull meanes of worſhip, for that were nothing els but to prove that worſhip before images were will-worſhip,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:6500:10"/> but they labour for this, that the Papists while they adore before images they give that unto the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which is proper unto God, &amp; the Papiſts in this que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion uſe not this defence, that images are lawful means of worship, but that the worship of images is relative, and reſolveth upon the paternes whoſe images they are.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That we may have a further inſight in this truth, we must learne, as in other parts of divine worship, ſo in our adoration before the bread, to diſtinguish betwixt that which is internall in the minde, and that which is externall in the ſenſes and geſtures of the body or (as the ſchoolemen ſpeake) betwixt the ſpirit of adoration, which they make the inward affection of ſubjecting our ſelfes to that which we adore, And the externall mark or ſigne of adoration, which they alſo call the materiall part of adoration, for ſuppoſe it were true that the whole thoughts and affections of the ſoule were taken up, and exerciſed about the thing ſignified in the Sacrament, and that nothing were intended but to render the whole worship unto God, yet the verie nature of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (which is well called the viſible word) of neceſsitie doth require that our eyes and therefore our geſtures, the bowing of our knees, and that whole materiall part of adoration be directed toward the elements in the act of receaving, in ſo farre that although the elements were nothing els to the minde but onlie ſignes to bring us to the right remembrance of the thing ſignified, it cannot be eshewed, but they muſt be the object of the outward adoration of the bodie, which is directed toward them, and therefore adoration before the bread, must needs be the adoration of the bread, even as the adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tien before the image, the adoration of the image, while the image to his minde, that adoreth, is nothing elſe but a ſigne, bringing the paterne to his remembrance.</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:6500:11"/>
               <p n="5">5. Since there be two kinds of divine worſhip, one immediat, as for exemple, <hi>Prayer, Thankſgiving, the religious hearing of the voice of God ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to us immediatlie:</hi> The other mediat, as the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie hearing of the word, and receaving of the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. It is both lawfull and ſuitable to uſe the geſture of adoration in Prayer, in thanksgiving, and when we hear the immediat voice of God, becauſe no viſible midle commeth in betwixt God and us that can be the object of our adoration, But in the ordinarie hearing of the word at the mouth of the Preacher, and in the act of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaving the Sacrament, it is neither ſuitable, nor lawful to adore; for that were to adore in a mediat worship, or to adore mediatlie, which both by force of truth, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion of both ſides must be Idolatrie.</p>
               <p n="6">6. It is therefore unlawfull to adore before the bread, or to kneel in the verie act of receaving the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, not onely by reaſon of the danger of bread wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, wherein the bread is adored in ſtead of Christ by the ignorant multitude, neither is it onely unlawfull, becauſe it is idolatrie to adore before the bread for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence and due regard of the Sacrament, which can not be avoided by them who adore according to the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the article of perth aſſemblie; But it is alſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull, becauſe adoration before the bread, even in the very nature of the action it ſelf, is idolatrie, neither is it poſsible for any man to make his adoration before the bread not to be Idolatrie, except he will take away the element that is the Sacrament it ſelf from the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which is impoſsible.</p>
               <p n="7">7. And therefore they are to be commended, who farre from all idolatrie, and from all perill and appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of idolatrie doe ſit or uſe an ordinarie table ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture in the ſupper of the Lord: Since neither the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:6500:11"/> Euangelifls nor the Apoſtle Paul have written ſo much as one word, which may give the least ſuſpition, or ground of conjecture, that Christ and his Apostles did change their ordinarie, and common forme of ſitting at table: Since it is certaine from the whole frame of the inſtitution that the ſupper of the Lord was an holy feast or banquet, and ſince by ſo doing the whole inſtitution of Christ, which is very many wayes defaced by kneeling, is keeped ſafe &amp; ſound. It is not farre from blaſphemie (ſayeth <hi>Paraeus)</hi> to ſay, that the Kirk hath with greater wiſdome made any change in the Eucharist, for what were that but to ſay, that the Kirk is wiſer then Christ himſelfe, as if he had not knowne well enough, what was able to procure greatest reverence to the Sacrament, or what should carrie with it the least perill, which is a Blaſphemie worthie of the followers of Antichrist.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Maſter</hi> William Cowper <hi>miniſter at Perth his letter, written before he was Bishop of Galloway, to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>.</hi> George Grahame <hi>Bishop of Dumblane, Anno</hi> 1606.</head>
               <p>BRother, <hi>I</hi> have receaved your commendations from B. which were needles, if you had keeped your wonted heart. As for me, <hi>I</hi> never hated you, your courſe wherein ye are entered <hi>I</hi> never loved. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the fruit ye enjoy be ſweet, yet the end ſhall prove it never grew on the tree of life. Doing in a worke of conſcience with doubting turneth light in darknes, whereupon followeth induration. Whereof it followeth that manie in our Kirk without feeling are courſers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst their brethren, that have done more good in the Kirk for edification of others then ever themſelfes did,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:6500:12"/> having neither eyes to ſee, nor hearts to feel how dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous their eſtate is, who can not riſe but with the fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of manie who in God have entered this ministrie, cloſing the fountaine that God hath opened. One of your owne told me, long ere the laſt Miniſters went to <hi>England,</hi> that they were written for to reaſon, but the end proved priſon, and no appearance of returning to ſome of them. Theſe are the first fruits of your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment. Here ye ſtand, and therefore I can not ſtand with you, except it be to witneſſe to God in mine heart againſt you, that ye have gone wrong. Ye hope in this courſe to doe good, but it is hard for you to worke mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles. At leaſt ye will hold of evill: But how shall ye draw in a yoke with them that are drawing on evill daylie. Ye will not goe beyond the caveats of the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall aſſemblie. But the anſwers given to the commiſsio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the Kirk at the last Parliament by the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellar (we enter not Bishops according to an act of the aſſemblie, but according to that which they were an hundreth yeares ſince) <hi>detexit fraudem.</hi> I heard it given, and ſo did the chiefe of themſelfes, <hi>A. B. C.</hi> ye skarre at them whom ye were blyth to ſee, ye like not the light ye loved, ye count theſe preachings unpleaſant, wherein ye were wont to rejoyce. Theſe may tell yow ye have fallen. Conſider your ſelf, where ye was, where ye are now, <hi>&amp; quantulum illud ſit propter quod nos reliquiſti.</hi> Thus loving yourſelf, and not your way, <hi>I</hi> end.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:6500:12"/>
               <head>Maſter <hi>Gawin Hammilton</hi> Bishop of <hi>Galloway</hi> was ſent up to Court by the reſt of the Bishops, after the convention of the Eſtates, which was holden about the end of Ianuarie 1609. I have here ſet down the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions or memorials recommended to him by the reſt of the Bishops, written by M. <hi>Iohn Spotſewood</hi> then pretendit Bishop of <hi>Glaſgow</hi> and ſubſcrived by him in name of the reſt.</head>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>Memorials to be proponed to his moſt excellent Majeſtie.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. YOu shall relate the proceedings of the late convention, and what affection ſome that were preſent keithed therein, that his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie may be for ſeene with mens diſpoſition, for the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter choyce of thoſe to whom the affaires shall be concre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dited.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. You shall remember the care we have had of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claiming the <hi>Marques</hi> of <hi>Huntlie,</hi> and the <hi>Earle</hi> of <hi>Arrall</hi> from their errours, and the ſmall profite we have ſeene thereof, and inſist for his Majeſties favour to the petition of our Letter.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Anent the Miniſters that are confined, your L. shall excuſe the requeeſt made by us in ſome of their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, shewing how it proceeded, &amp; further declare that of late they have taken courſe to give in ſupplications to the counſell for their enlarging to a certaine time, for doing their particular buſineſſe at ſeſsion &amp; otherwayes in the country, &amp; that ſome of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> have purchaſed licence by the votes of the counſell, albeit we opponed. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore beſeek his Majeſt. to remember the counſell, that the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:6500:13"/> confining of theſe Miniſters, was for faults done by them to his H. ſelf, &amp; that they should be acknowledged and conf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſed to his Majeſtie and his H. pleaſure under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood therein before the grant of any favour, otherwiſe they ſhall undoe all that hath beene hitherto followed for the peace of the Kirk.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Touching the erections, it is our humble deſire to his Majeſtie that the Noblemen, in whoſe favours the ſame have beene past, may take order for the proviſion of their Kirks, according to the conditions made in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, or then diſcharge their erections: which ſeemes beſt to be done by an act of this enſuing ſeſsion of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, for which his Majeſties warrant would be had. And ſome ſuch like courſe would be taken for the prelacies erected, which have past alſo the conſtant plat, that the preſentation of Miniſters to the modified ſtipends at the vacantie of the Church ſhould be in his Majeſties hand, whereunto though his Majeſties ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe commandement was given of before, no heed was taken by ſuch as had the charge of affaires.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Since this matter of the commiſſariats importeth ſo much to the reformation of our Church governement, as this being reſtored in a litle time, the rest may be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied which will be wanting, it ſhall be good to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber it by a ſerious letter to my Lord of Dumbar, that we may know in due time what is to be expected. And ſince our greateſt hinderance is found to be in the ſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, of whom the most part are ever in heart oppoſite unto us, and forbeare not to keith it when they have oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, you ſhall humblie intreat his Majeſtie to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member our ſute for the kirkmens place, according to the first inſtitution, and that it may take at this time ſome beginning, ſince the place vacant was even from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning in the hands of the ſpirituall ſide with ſome one
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:6500:13"/> kirkman or other till now, which might it be obtained, as were moſt eaſie by his Majeſties direction and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, there should be ſeene a ſuddaine change of many humours in that eſtate, and the commonwealth would find the profite thereof.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Anent our conference with the miniſtrie, your L. will declare the time that is appointed, and reaſons of the continuation of the ſame.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Becauſe in the time of Parliament cheeflie, it ſhould be expedient to have the Biſhops to teach in the pulpits of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> his Majeſtie would be pleaſed to commend this to my Lord of <hi>Dumbar</hi> by a particular letter, and to require alſo the Miniſters of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> to deſire their help at that time, if it were for no other end, but to teſtifie their unitie and conſent of minds to the Eſtates.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Becauſe the Kirk of <hi>Leith</hi> lyeth deſtitute in a ſort through the Biſhop of Roſse his age, and the impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonement of <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Iohn Murrey,</hi> and that the ſaid <hi>M. Iohn</hi> is no wayes minded, as appeareth, to give his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie ſatisfaction, neither were it meet, in reſpect of his carriage, that he should returne to that miniſtrie, and to inſist in his deprivation with the Commiſsioners might perhaps breed us a new difficultie, if his Majeſtie ſhall be pleaſed, we doe hold it most convenient for the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand, that the ſaid <hi>M. Iohn</hi> be conveened before the counſell by his Majeſties command, and by them charged to waid in the towne of <hi>Newabbey,</hi> and ſome miles about, having libertie to teach that people, among whom he ſhall find ſome other ſubject to worke upon then the ſtate of Biſhops. And for the proviſion of <hi>Leith,</hi> that his Majeſtie would be pleaſed to command the presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> in regarde of the Biſhop of <hi>Roſſe</hi> his age, and the ſaid M. <hi>Iohns</hi> tranſportation by his
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:6500:14"/> H. appointment, to have care that the ſaid Kirk of <hi>Leith</hi> be planted with all convenient diligence by M. <hi>David Lindſey</hi> ſometimes Miniſter at <hi>Sant An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drewis,</hi> for whom both the people is earnest, and we may have ſufficient aſſurance to his Majeſties ſervice. And incaſe the ſaid presbyterie prove wilfull, that ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther letter to the ſame effect may be ſent to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsioners of the generall aſſemblie, who may take order to ſee that matter ended, if ſuch shall be his Majeſties pleaſure, and this would be done with all diligence con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient.</p>
                  <p>We cannot but remember alſo the miſorder keeped in the countrie, that once was happily repreſſed, wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of gunnes and piſtols, and humblie beſeech his Maj. that ſome new courſe may be eſtablished for ſearching of ſuch perſons, and delating of them to the counſell, that they may be punished, and the Theſaurer may have commandement to make choiſe in everie countrie of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine that shall be thought fittest to ſearch, who shall be knowne onelie to his L. ſelf, and ſatisfie them for their paines, to the end this inſolence may be reſtrained. Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularlie it would be forbidden in the granting of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsions, that this libertie be not permitted, for this is one of the cauſes of their ſo open dealing, as ſaid is.</p>
                  <p>Theſe particulars, your L. would have care to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pone to his Majeſt. at ſome fit time, and ſee the anſwers thereof diſpatched accordingly.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Glaſgow</hi> by the warrant and at the deſire of the rest of my Lords the Bishops.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:6500:14"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Maſter</hi> George Glaidſtones <hi>ſent this let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter following to the King in Auguſt</hi> 1612. <hi>whereby the reader may perceave what were their plots and preparations before the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament following in October where the act of Glaſgow was ratified, or rather alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Moſt gratious Soveraigne.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>AS it hath pleaſed your Maj. to direct mee, and my Lord your Majeſties Secretarie for adviſing anent our affairs to be handled in this approaching parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſo happilie did <hi>I</hi> find him, and my Lord of Glaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gow both in this towne, and conveened them both im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatlie after mine arriving, and with good adviſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment we have made choiſe of theſe things which are moſt neceſsarie, and have omitted theſe articles which may ſeeme to carie envie or ſuſpition, or which your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie by your royall authoritie might not performe by your ſelf. But we all hold faſt this concluſion, that it is moſt neceſſarie and convenient, both for your Majeſties ſervice, and weill of the Church, that the Day viz. the 12. of October ſhall hold preciſelie, to the which the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament was proclaimed upon the 24. of this instant. <hi>I</hi> will aſſure your Majeſt. that the verie evill will, which is caried to my Lord Chancelor by the nobilitie and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, is like to make us great ſtore of friendſhip, for they know him to be our profeſsed enemie, and he diſſembled it not. <hi>I</hi> thank God, that it pleaſed your M. to make choiſe of my Lord Secretary to be our Formaliſt, and adviſer of our acts. For we finde him wiſe, fast &amp; ſecret We ſhall not be idle in the mean time to prepare ſuch, as have vote to incline the right way. All men do follow us and hunt
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:6500:15"/> for our favour, upon report of your Majeſties good ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance of me and the Bishop of <hi>Cathnes,</hi> and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding for my Lord of Glaſgow, and the procurement of this Parliament without advice of the Chancellar. And if your Majeſtie will continue theſe ſhining beames, and ſhowes of your Majeſties favour, doubtleſſe the purpoſe that ſeemes most difficill, will be facilitat to your Majeſties great honour and our credit, which, if it were greater then it is, your Majeſtie could receave no intereſſe. For beſides that no eſtate may ſay, that they are your Majeſties creaturs as we may ſay, ſo there is none whoſe ſtanding is ſo ſlipperie, when your Majeſtie ſhall frowne as we. For at your Majeſties nodde we must either ſtand or fall. But we referre the more am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple declaration of theſe purpoſes and other points of your Majeſties ſervice, to the ſufficencie of my Lord of Glaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gow, and my good Lord Secretarie, the fourteenth Biſhop of this Kingdome. But my Lord of Glaſgow and I am contending, to which of the two Provinces he ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaine. Your Majeſtie who is our great Archbiſhop must decide it. Thus after my most humble and heartie thanks for your Majeſties good acceptance, and gratious diſpatch lately which hath filled the eares of all this Kingdome, I beſeech God to heape upon your Majeſtie the plentie of all ſpirituall and temporall bleſsings for ever, <hi>I</hi> rest</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Edinburgh <date>the last of August 1612.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Yours Majeſties moſthumble ſubject and Servitour <hi>S. Andrewis.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:6500:15"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Maſter</hi> William Struther <hi>one of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of</hi> Edinburgh, <hi>and a Conformitane, howbeit he was content to accept a fat Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhopricke, yet was content in end to forgoe the lean ceremonies to live in the greater eaſe and peace, as this letter following dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to the Earle of</hi> Airth, <hi>to be preſented to his Majeſtie, teſtifieth.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>My very good Lord,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Viſite your L. with this letter, and that for the end which I ſpoke mcore largelie in conference, ever for the peace of this poore Kirk, which rent ſo gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouſlie for ceremonies. There is alſo ſome ſurmiſes of farther novations of <hi>organes, Liturgies</hi> and ſuch like, which greatly augments the grief of people, but the wiſer ſort aſſure themſelfes of his Majeſties royall wiſdome and moderation, that his Majeſtie would impoſe no new thing, if his Majeſtie were timouſlie informed of theſe, and the like reaſons.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe King Iames of happie memorie made the <hi>Marques</hi> of <hi>Hammilton</hi> promiſe in his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties name to all the Eſtates of this Land ſolemnely in face of Parliament, that this Church ſhould not be urged with any moe novations then theſe five articles, that then were preſented to the Parliament, upon which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe the Parliament reſted, and gave way the more chearfully that theſe articles should paſſe in act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Nixt, becauſe the motion, that is ſaid to be made to his Maieſtie of theſe novations, is made by and beſide
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:6500:16"/> the knowledge and conſcience of the kirk of this land, who are heavily diſpleaſed for that motion, and more becauſe it is alleadged to have been in their name, who knowes nothing thereof but by report.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Becauſe our church lyes already groaning under two woundes, the first of the erection of Biſhops, the other of kneeling. But if a third be inſticted, there is no appearance but of a diſsipation of this church. In the first people were onely anlookers on Biſhops ſtate. The ſecond touched them more in celebration of the holy ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, but yet leſt arbitrarie to them, But this third will be greater, becauſe in the whole body of publike worſhip they ſhall be forced to ſuffer novelties.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Becauſe the Biſhops are already <hi>publici odii vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctimae</hi> and borne down with contempt, and that vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is intollerable, when they depoſe any brother for not conformitie, they ſcarcely can finde an expectant to fill the empty place, and that becauſe they become ſo odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to the flock, that they can doe no good in their mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrie. But if any farther novation be brought in, the Biſhops will finde ten for one to be depoſed, and that of thoſe who have already given obedience to the five arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, who will rather chuſe to forſake their places, then to enter in a new fire of combuſtion.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Laſtly, becauſe it is obſerved by ſuch as are judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, that the former ſhiſmes have ſhaken the hearts of the people in religion, and hath produced <hi>odium vati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nianum</hi> among brethren, poprie is encreaſed in the land, and if any farther come in, it will be ſeen, that uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally people will be made ſuſceptible of any religion, and turne Atheists in groſſe.</p>
               <p>Your L. knowes I am not one of theſe who ſtand out againſt order, but doe ſuffer for mine obedience, and therefore the more boldly I ſuggeſt theſe reaſons unto
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:6500:16"/> your L. <hi>I</hi> dwell in the moſt eminent part of this land, and ſo have occaſion te ſee more what is the fruit of a ſhiſme. I profeſſe an unſpeakable griefe to ſee any thing done that may trouble the peace of a church, and devide the hearts of a good people from a good king. Our fire is ſo great already, that it hath more need of water to quench it, then oile to augment it.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Edinburgh <date>the 28 of Ianuar. 1630.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
